Guide to the Donald C. Stone Papers relating to the United Nations, 1943-1949 AIS.1971.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Special Issues and NGO Documents, V.
  A Non-Governmental Organization (NGO) is defined by the U.N. as a non-profit, voluntary citizens' group, which is organized on a local, national or international level to address issues in support of the public good. Over a thousand lobbies and civic monitors register annually with the United Nations' DPI.
  Stone would have seen numerous NGO-authored reports, petitions, and speech transcriptions as an agent of the federal government. Related documents include a telegraphed petition to U.S. State Department, signed by, among others, physicist Albert Einstein and Ruth Crawford Mitchell, director of the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms.
  - Trieste Committee Reports and Resolutions (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - NGO Reports and Petitions (Box 8, Folder 14)
- United States Executive Office of the President
  The Bureau of the Budget was established in 1921 as a part of the Department of the Treasury by the Budget and Accounting Act of 1921, which was signed into law by president Warren G. Harding. The Bureau of the Budget was moved to the Executive Office of the President in 1939 and was run by Harold D. Smith during the government's rapid expansion of spending during the Second World War. This series covers Dr Donald Stone's work in the executive branch, primarily after he was transfered to the Bureau of the Budget as the Assistant Director.
  The first subseries of note is the Bureau of the Budget, containing papers pertaining to Stone's time as assistant director of the Bureau. The content of the documents range from management of the Bureau, staff memmors, the founding of the Bureau as a distinct entity within the federl government, and an administrative diary by Stone himself.
  The next subseries of note is Stone's Administrative Observations, having been contained in a binder upon acquisition by the archives. In it, Stone records his tasks, schedule, and provides input on his opinions with regards to the prosecution of the war and the handling of the Bureau.
  The final subseries of note is that of Executive Reorganization. These papers are wide in variety, some arising from Stone himself as the assistant director, others from those outside of government. They all share in common the discussion of reorganizing the federal government, in the form of reports, acts of Congress, memos, periodicals, and conference speeches.
  - Bureau of the Budget
    - Management, Nov 24, 1943 - Aug 3, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Organization and Function, May 12, 1939 - Jun 20, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Staff, Apr 29, 1941 - Oct 8, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Establishment, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ramspeck Committee, May 27, 1943 - Jul 5, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Administrative Diary, Apr 25, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - International Lessons Learned, Aug 1942 - Oct 7, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Observations
    - 9 September 1939-30 December 1939 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 5 January 1940-7 April 1940 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1 July 1943-29 December 1943 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 25 February 1944-15 August 1944 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Executive Reorganization
    - Proposal for Service of a General Adminstration of the National Government, Oct 20, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Excerpts from Reorganization of Executive Departments, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Speech (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Acts of Congress and Plans for Reorganization, 1939-40 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Papers from Outside of Government, Feb 1947 - Apr 4, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Personal Dispatches, July 7, 1942 - June 29, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Personal Dispatches, April 25, 1944 - May 21, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Notes and Reports, January 12, 1941 - September 18, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Notes and Reports, December 4,1943 - October 23, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Notes and Reports, Winter 1945- March 6, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Reports, September 23, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Notes and Reports, Mar 16, 1948 - Oct 6, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- United Nations, Extended
  The scope of these additional papers concerning internaitonal matters is little beyond that which has already been catalogued. Most intereting are papers arising from during and shortly after the Second World War which deal with the management of liberated areas. Considering Dr. Stone's future work with the Marshall Plan, these papers provide an interesting precursor to his opinions on the matter and his post-war plans.
  - Liberated Areas, Jun 13, 1945 - Oct 6, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Economic Cooperation Administration/Marshall Plan, Jan 17, 1947 - Jul 8, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Personal Dispatches, Dec 6, 1945 - Jan 16, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Institutional Proposals, Sep 7, 1944 - Oct 6, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - US Commission to UNESCO, Sep 15-17, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Coalition to Improve Management of State and Local Government
  This sries concerns itself with Dr. Stone's work with the advocacy group Coalition to Improve Management of State and Local Government, one which he joined after the war. The purpose of the Coalition was to provide state and local governments with reports, management guides, and access to professionals who could help move city, county, and state governments towards their policy objectives. This series in particular focuses almost exclusively with Allegheny County, wherein Dr. Stone personally oversaw development. There are four subseries of note
  The Allegheny County CODE Project, as organized before arrival at the archive, deals with reports, guides, and special papers concerned with the management of Allegheny County government. After Pennsylvania passed Act 62 in 1972, granting cities the right to Home Rule, Allegheny county embarked on a spirited campaign to reform the executive and legislative functions of the county government, as well as improve efficiency in general. Contained wihin this subseries is an additional subseries pertaining to documents which Dr. Stone used as a reference form outside Pennsylvania, such as Wisconsin and Delaware's constitutions and county statutes.
  The Mayor Peter Flaherty subseries covers Dr. Stone's involvement in the nascent Flaherty administration following his election in 1970, through to 1977 when Mayor Flaherty was nominated as the Deputy Attorney General in the Carter Administration. Contained herein are papers, memos, and correspondences between Dr. Stone and Peter Flaherty where Dr. Stone offers to send GSPIA students as volunteers for the Flaherty administration, and his personal misgivings about Flaherty as a Deputy Attorney General.
  Handbooks covers published books and manuals from the Coalition, designed to help government officials navigate their new posts. This subseries also contains the Strategic Goals of the CODE Project, wherein the particular annual goals for Allegheny County are recorded and quotas made.
  Finally, the Allegheny County Office of Management and Budget covers reports, memos, and updates on various programs. The OMP as established between 1987 and 1988 as a new division of the Department of Administration, with the purpose of improving productivity and spearhead projects and studies with county-wide scope. One particularly salient folder contains documents pertiaing to, as Stone described them, "Work Programs", which covers the broad strokes of what the OMP set out to do, mainly containing various programs and their status.
  - Alleghey County CODE Project
    - Standards for Local Public Authorities in PA, Jun 17, 1992 - Oct 5, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Standards for Local Public Authorities in PA, Management Guide, Aug 1992 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Management Guides, Sep 1991-Feb 1992 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Preperation for Directors' Retreat, March 23, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Summer Intern Program, Jun 1988 - Aug 18, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Nemacolin Woodlands, Farmington, PA, 1991 - Mar 18, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Solid Waste, Jan 1990 - Oct 7, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Performance Measures, Oct 31, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Quarterly Reports, Jan/Feb 1990 - Jun 26, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Correspondence, 1980 - Oct 18, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - The County Administrator, Oct 1986 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Managing Interdependence Between Sectors, Nov/Dec 1991 - Jan 1992 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Special Paper 2, Feb 1989 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Special Paper 4, May 1990 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Special Paper 5, Jan 1992 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Co-Op with ASPA, Jun 11, 1993 - Mar 1994 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Reports on Allegheny County, Feb 11, 1986 - Apr 26, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - PA and Non-PA References
      - PA Constitution (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - An Examination, Mar/Apr 1988 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Three Year Retrospective and Charts, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Wisconsin County Statutes, Jun 1, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Delaware (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Barnstable Charter Commission, Oct 27, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Iowa, Jun 7, 1988 - Jul 12, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - County Home Rule: New Options for Counties (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Mayor Peter Flaherty
    - GSPIA, Dec 3, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Inauguration, Jan 5, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Dec 13, 1969 - Mar 6, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Reports and Letters, Dec 18, 1969 - Mar 11, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Draft Memos and Proposals, Nov 23, 1969 - Jan 5, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Dr. Stone, Nov 18, 1969 - May 22, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Planning How a Mayor-Elect Takes Over His Post, Feb 23, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Handbooks
    - Analytical Methods Reports, Aug 1991 - 1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Intergovernmental Cooperation Handbook, Apr 1990 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Township Commissioners Handbook, Jun 1987 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Borough Councilmen's Handbook, Jun 1987 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Township Supervisors Handbook, Jan 1986 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - "It Makes a Difference", Intergovernmental Cooperation, PA Department of Community Affairs, Jun 1988 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Strategic Planning Project, Goals Program, Oct 21, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny County Office of Mnagement and Productivity
    - Work Programs, Feb 1, 1988 - 25 Oct 1988 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Updates, Mar 1989 - Feb 28, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Presentation Overview, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Memoranda, Oct 29, 1986 - Feb 19, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Awards Breakfast, Feb 23, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Reports, June 1986 - Sep 1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Reports, Nov 1988-Feb 1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Charts, Inerviews, and Newspaper Clippings
  This series contains newspaper clippings from Dr. Stone's lifetime whic deal either with him directly or the organization he was apart of at the time, as well as charts of the executive branch, photographs of Dr. Stone, and an interview with him in October 1992. A transcript of the interview is contained within the subseries "Interview with Donald Stone", as well as letters and articles which discuss the interview. Miscellaneous contains poems, quotes, cards for christian church services, invitations, and other documents which could not be placed neatly in another series.
  - Interview with Donald Stone
    - Foreign Service History Center, Mar 8, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Jan 5 - Mar 7, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Public Works Oral Interview, Oct - Dec 30, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Graduate School for City Managers, 1925-6 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Cincinnati, 1927-9 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - International City Managers Association, 1930-3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Public Administration Service, 1934-9 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Executive (Re)Organization, 1939; 1953 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Bureau of the Budget, 1939-1948 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Academic and Theological Talks on ECA, 1949-1953 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - UN/ECA, 1943-1953 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Academic Career, 1953-1961, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Consulting/Coalition, 1979-1992 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Misc., Undated, and Supplemental, 1940-1955 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Personal Advocacy; Creation of a More Just, Peaceful, ad Caring Society, May 1992 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Invitations, Jun 9, 1950 - Mar 20, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Articles (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Quotes (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Letters and Handwritten Notes, Feb 27, 1952 - Dec 27, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Christian/Church Related Matters, Mar 15, 1953 - Nov 5, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Government Papers, Dec 21, 1932 - Apr 9, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Poems (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Government Charts (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Awards and Commendations
  This series contains documents attesting to Dr. Stone's numerous achievements, either requesting he attend a conference to be bestowed with an award, articles covering the awards he had won, and journals discussing awards named after him. Contained in this series are several plaques which are too big to fit in a standard box and, as such, have been moved into an oversize container.
  - Documents
    - Plaques, Apr 1, 1959 - Jun 13, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Awards Invitations, 1979 - Sep 15, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Newspaper/Journal Announcements, Jun 1, 1980 - Jun 12, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Program Details, Apr 14, 1980 - Jun 3, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Oversize Plaques
- Private Sector Advocacy
  Prive Sector AdocacyScope and Content Notes
  This Series covers Dr. Stone's tenure at various non-governmental and non-academic institutions which focused on public administration. Two that are especially of note are the American Society of Public Administration and the Public Administration Service, both of which Dr. Stone was a founding member of.
  The Public Administration Service (PAS) was chartered in 1933 in the State of Illinois to provide professional management consulting services, applied research, technical assistance, and training to government and quasi-government departments and agencies, with a primary focus on local government. PAS would publish the book The President and the Presidency in 1949, which was one of the first attempts to define executive government. PAS continued this research focus throughout its first twenty years, creating a respectable list of published books under its imprint, while being funded exclusively through grants. After the Second World War, and particularly by the early 1950s, PAS began to work intensively overseas.
  The American Society for Public Administration was founded in 1939 by Louis Brownlow, William E. Mosher, Donald C. Stone, Charles A. Beard, Harold D. Smith, Luther Gulick, and others. The ASPA sponsorsed the Public Administration Review since 1939, established the the National Academy of Public Administration (NAPA) as part of ASPA in 1967, only to formally separate in 1970, and, in 1981, established with NAPA of National Public Service Awards, of which Stone would be an early recipient.
  Wihin the Subseries covering the ASPA are membership reports, addresses to conferences hosted by the ASPA, newsletters, and other internal organizational documents.
  Within the subseries concerning the PAS, documents have retained the order in which they were recieved, with the exception of documents pertaining to the Press Bureau Round Table and Police Effectiveness. Otherise, all documents herein come from a binder labeled "Public Administration Service" as organized by Stone himself.
  - Social Science Research Council
    - Committee on Public Administration Conferences, Jul 22 and Nov 5, 1942 - May 29, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Public Adminstration
    - National Council Meeting, Apr 3, 1992 - Dec 6, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Organizationl Documents, Jun 1992 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Addresses to Conferences and Meetings, Dec 28, 1939 - Dec 29, 1941; 3 Feb 1993 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Explanatory Statement (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Membership Report, May 31, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - SUPA's Contribution to Government Recognized, Mar/Apr 1989 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Newsletters, Mar/Apr 1989; 1993 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Institute of Public Administration, Mar 26, 1946; May 28, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Public Adminstration Service
    - Miscellaneous and Report Forms, Oct 1, 1936 - Jun 1937 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Promotion Materials, Nov 6, 1935 - Nov 12, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Proposals, Sep 12, 1934 - Dec 17, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Staff, May 7, 1937 - Dec 20, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Professional Records, Jul 1, 1937 - May 17, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Staff Memos, Feb 13, 1936 - Feb 3, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Accounting and Reporting (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Police Effectiveness and Memoranda, Feb 1934 - Mar 7, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Press Bureau Round Table, Mar 28-9, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 18)
- Academic Career
  This series deals with Dr. Stone's academic career after World War Two, wherein he taught for several ears at American University before working with the University of Pittsburgh to found the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs in 1957, to promote the learning of public administration at home and abroad in the growing field of international administration. He would remain the dean of GSPIA until he retired from the position in 1968 while still teaching at the University of Pittsburgh. In 1975, he moved to Carnegie Mellon Univeristy's Heinz College of Information systems and Public Policy, and set up the Coalition to Improve Management of State and Local Government. In 1990, he moved with the executive committee of the Coalition to Indiana and worked with the Indiana University School of Public and Environmental Affairs until his retirement from academia in 1992.
  Docments contained herein consist of lecture notes and outlines for class discussions from Stone's time at American University; several papers concerned with what can be dubbed "Management Theory", as the papers arise either from Stone's time in academia but without a date, or are from outside sources which Dr. Stone felt were worth preserving; and lecture notes from his time at GSPIA, Heinz School, and Indiana's SPEA. Similarly, there are five papers from five different authors concerned with the Institutional Presidency and the Executive Office, from the National Academy ogf Public Administration, written for a conference in april 1980.
  - Management Theory
    - Works by Dr. Stone (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Ethics, Jul 1973 - Feb 26, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Outside Literature, Sep 20, 1939 - Jun 14, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Notes on the Governmental Executive, Jan 15, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - GSPIA, CMU Heinz School, Indiana University SEPA
    - Indiana University, School of Public and Evironmental Affairs/Coalition, Jan 25, 1993 - Mar 3, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - University of Pittsburgh, GSPIA, Oct 16, 1961 - Jan 19, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Carnegie-Mellon University, Spring 1993 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Other Schools, May 14, 1953; Juun 17, 1967; Oct 28, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - American University, 1947-1953
    - Course Outlines and Class Discussions, May 21, 1946 - Apr 5, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Course Outlines and Class Discussions, 13-14 Feb 1950 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Course Outlines and Class Discussions, 21 Feb 1950 - 24 Feb 1953 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Class Transript, Feb 18, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Paper Subjects (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - National Academy of Public Administration
    - Index and L. Salamon, Apr 10-11, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Heclo, Apr 10-11, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - I.M. Destler, Apr 10-11, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - F.C. Mosher, Apr 10-11, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - The Institutional Presidency, Don Price, Apr 1, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 18)